Finding Aid for the UNITE HERE Records LSC.2325
UCLA Library Special Collections
UNITE HERE records
1920-2013
1980-1990
UCLA Library Special Collections
UNITE HERE (Organization).
LSC.2325
33.8 Linear Feet (25 boxes, 15 cartons, 11 flat boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, 1 flat file)
3 Born-digital Carriers (3 unprocessed hard drives)
UNITE-HERE Local 11 traces its origins to the Hotel and Restaurant Employees and Bartenders International union founded in 1891 and has been active in Southern California since the 1930s. Local 11 partnered with other labor and community organizations to play a key role in reviving the Los Angeles labor movement during the 1990s and 2000s. Local 11 grew through mergers with HERE locals in Santa Monica (Local 814) in 2002 and Orange County/Long Beach (Local 681) in 2008. HERE International merged with UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees) to form UNITE-HERE in July, 2004. This collection consists of materials documenting UNITE-HERE Locals 11, 814 and 681 and includes files of union leaders Maria Elena Durazo, Kurt Petersen and Tom Walsh, Executive Board meeting minutes, newspaper coverage in English and Spanish of union campaigns, union serial publications, booklets and videos, television coverage of organizing campaigns, transcribed oral histories, photographs and ephemera.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Box 52 containing quilt top banner requires special handling for access. Please contact Special Collections reference (spec-coll@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed digital and audiovisual materials. Digital and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital and audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
UNITE HERE Local 11; Gift; 2015.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9982131163606533
Biography/History
UNITE-HERE Local 11 traces its origins to the Hotel and Restaurant Employees and Bartenders International Union founded in 1891 and has been active in Southern California since the 1930s. Along with Justice for janitors, LAANE and the County Federation of Labor, it played a key role in reviving the Los Angeles labor movement during the 1990s and 2000s. HERE International merged with UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees Union) to form UNITE-HERE in July, 2004.
Local 11 has been involved with high profile organizing activities throughout Los Angeles. In the 1990s they led a multi-year campaign to unionize the New Otani Hotel in Little Tokyo through a card check process as well as campaigns to unionize workers at the Ambassador Hotel and luxury hotels on Santa Monica's beach front. In 2004 they participated in a national campaign with major hotels across the United States and won important concessions from local hotels. The local has been a strong proponent of Living Wage and Minimum Wage Ordinances in L.A., Santa Monica and Long Beach and helped create the Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy (LAANE).
Historically waiters, bartenders, waitresses, kitchen and cleaning staff organized into separate locals or chapters. By the 1970s, most locals were geographically based, and included both front of the house staff (e.g., waiters and bartenders) and back of the house staff (e.g. kitchen, cleaning, etc.). During the 1980s and 1990s, the Los Angeles and Santa Monica HERE locals experienced leadership strains, with long serving leaders failing to respond to an increasingly immigrant workforce and anti-union climate
Maria Elena Durazo, emerged as a reform leader of Local 11 in the late 1980s, leading several successful organizing drives for HERE, and championing the cause of back of the house staff, mainly Latin American immigrant women. In 1989, Durazo was elected Local 11 president, becoming one of the first Latina leaders of a major American union local. She would eventually serve as Secretary Treasurer of the Los Angeles County Federation of Labor (2005 to 2014). In 1995, Local 814 in Santa Monica was placed in trusteeship and in an election the following year, organizer Tom Walsh became president. Kurt Petersen, who joined the United Farm Workers of Washington State as an organizer, started his association with HERE in 1995 and has served the Local and national organization in various capacities.
The geographic scope of Local 11 grew through mergers with local unions in Santa Monica (Local 814) in 2002, and Orange County/Long Beach (Local 681) in 2008. Tom Walsh became the president of Local 11 after the mergers. The organization, with a membership of over 20,000 in 2018, embraces workers throughout Southern California, with a diverse membership from many immigrant communities as well as African-Americans, Latinos, and Asian-Americans. Industries represented include hotels, casinos, foodservice and retail airport concessions, stadiums and restaurants. Through grassroots mobilization of workers and community allies, Local 11 has improved working conditions, wages, and benefits for their members, transforming traditionally low-wage jobs to middle class jobs, and successfully participates in labor-management partnerships with employers to resolve issues in the workplace.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of materials related to the UNITE HERE Local 11 labor union. Included are files documenting UNITE HERE Local 11, Local 814, and Local 681. The Local 11 records represent files of union leaders Maria Elena Durazo, Kurt Petersen, and Tom Walsh; Executive Board meeting minutes, and newspaper and television coverage of union events and working conditions. Local 814 records include files from Kurt Petersen, Tom Walsh, Bill Granfield, and Victor Valenzuela. The Local 681 records are largely union serial publications going back to the 1940s, The Mixer and Server and Catering Industry Employee, union booklets documenting wage scale and working condition agreements, union Bylaws and photographs. Union leader files document organizing efforts on behalf of the employees of Southern California hotels and restaurants including Miramar Sheraton and Loews in Santa Monica, among others; legal matters, many involving the NLRB; newspaper clippings, union flyers, videos and publications, and anti-union employer documents, shop steward training materials, photographs, oral history interviews, and ephemera. Events represented include the Immigrant Worker Freedom Ride (IWFR), the Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy (LAANE) Santa Monica Living Wage campaign, LAX airport organizing campaigns, and Century Boulevard hotel organizing, among others.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged into the following series:
Series 1: Local 11 records (1952-2013, bulk 1980s-2012)
Subseries 1.1 Meeting Minutes (1952-1954, 1961-1963, 1972-1982, 1994, undated)
Subseries 1.2 Kurt Petersen files (circa 1980s-2012)
Subseries 1.3 Tom Walsh files (circa 1970s-circa 2004)
Subseries 1.4 Maria Elena Durazo files (1989-2008)
Subseries 1.5 News clippings (1994-2013)
Subseries 1.6 Photographs and ephemera (1970s, 1991-2004, 1999, circa 2008)
Series 2: Local 814 records (1950-2003)
Subseries 2.1 Kurt Petersen files (circa 1980s-2004)
Subseries 2.2 Tom Walsh files (circa 1980s-circa 1990s, 2001)
Subseries 2.3 Bill Granfield files (1988-1997, 1999)
Subseries 2.4 Victor Valenzuela files (circa 1950s-1993)
Subseries 2.5 Gary Guthman files (1988-1990)
Subseries 2.6 Photographs and ephemera (1996-2002)
Series 3: Local 681 records (1920-1994, 1999-2004)
Labor unions -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; UNITE HERE (Organization) -- Archives
- Series 1: Local 11 Records, 1952-2013; 1980-2012
  Scope and Content
  The series consists of materials related to the work of UNITE HERE Local 11. Included are files from union leaders Maria Elena Durazo, Kurt Petersen, and Tom Walsh; Executive Board meeting minutes, chronological newsclippings in English and Spanish compiled by a union member identified as Carlitos, photographs, and ephemera. Union leader files may include newspaper clippings, union flyers and publications, a small amount of court case documentation, anti-union literature published by employers, shop steward training materials, and photographs. Materials represent events such as the International immigrant Workers Freedom Ride (IWFR) and LAANE's Century Boulevard hotels organizing campaign, among others; efforts on behalf of employees from Southern California hotels such as Hilton, Hyatt, Delfina, New Otani, and Sheraton, among others; and legal matters involving the National Labor Relations Board (NLRB). Also included are a small amount of buttons, posters, T-shirts, and a quilt top banner, created by hotel workers. Audiovisual materials include Immigrant Workers Freedom Ride videos, and Local 11 produced videos.
  Organization and Arrangement
  The series is arranged into the following subseries:
  Subseries 1.1 Executive Board Meeting Minutes (1952-1954, 1961-1963, 1972-1982, 1994, undated)
  Subseries 1.2 Kurt Petersen files (circa 1980s-2012)
  Subseries 1.3 Tom Walsh files (circa 1970s-circa 2004)
  Subseries 1.4 Maria Elena Durazo files (1989-2008)
  Subseries 1.5 News clippings (1994-2013)
  Subseries 1.6 Photographs and ephemera (1970s, 1991-2004, 1999, circa 2008)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed digital and audiovisual materials. Digital and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the file level. All requests to access processed materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Subseries 1.1: Executive Board Meeting minutes, 1952-1994
    The meeting minutes document the work of the Local 11 Executive Board during the early 1950s and 1960s, 1972-1982, and 1994. Additionally included is a Grievance Processing and Settlement / Arbitration Preparation and Presentation multi-page document.
    Minutes are arranged in loose chronological order.
    - Executive Board meeting minutes, 1952-1980 (Box 8, Folder 1-19)
    - Executive board meeting minutes, 1981-1994 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - Grievance Processing and Settlement/Arbitration Preparation and Presentation documentation, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 1.2: Kurt Petersen files, 1980s-2012
    Kurt Petersen files document Local 11 efforts on behalf of employees employed at Southern California hotels and restaurants. Includes documentation concerning hotels such as Hilton and Hyatt, among others, a small number of files related to the Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy (LAANE) Century Boulevard living wage campaign, anti union material, ephemera, articles pertaining to union and labor activities, and a small amount of union-related agreements.
    Files are arranged alphabetically by file titles.
    - 10 Cities 10 Times Stronger pamphlet, undated (Box 9, Folder 66)
    - 410 K article, 2008 August 4 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Action Santa Monica, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - Agreement by and between Hotel-Restaurant Employer's Council of Southern California, Inc. and Local 11 Effective April 16, 1998 to April 15, 2004, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Agreement by and between Los Angeles Hotel Employer's Council For Millennium Biltmore Hotel, Sheraton Universal Hotel, Westin Century Plaza, Wilshire Grand Hotel & Centre, Hyatt West Hollywood, Regent Beverly Wilshire Hotel and Westin Bonaventure.and UNITE HERE Local 11 (Effective October 15, 2004 to November 30, 2006), undated (Box 9, Folder 67)
    - Agreement By and Between Sheraton Four Points LAX and UNITE HERE Local 11 (Effective April 7, 2008 to May 1, 2011), undated (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - Andy Stern, 2005 January 30-2006 February 8 (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - Anti-union campaign tips, undated (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - Anti-union captive audience meeting, undated (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - Anti-union Checkers, 1993 August 20 (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - Anti-union Glendale Hilton, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - Anti-union Hilton, 2004-2005 (Box 9, Folder 53)
    - Anti-union La Opinión article, 2005 October 19 (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - Anti-union Marriott, 1987 August (Box 9, Folder 55)
    - Anti-union New Jersey, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 56)
    - Anti-union propaganda about dues, undated (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Anti-union propaganda Four Points, 2005 April 8 (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - Anti-union propaganda Hyatt Long Beach, 2008-2009 (Box 9, Folder 68)
    - Anti-union propaganda Westin LAX, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 58)
    - Anti-union research, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Anti-union Sheraton Grande, 1992 September 22 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Anti-worker decisions from the NLRB, 2005 March (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Articles about hotels and workers, 1998 January 23-2005 September (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - Avion (Four Points by Sheraton), 2004-2005 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Avion strategy - Century Corridor: Los Angeles' Missed Opportunity flyer, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Boycott, 2004 Nov 29-2004 Dec 3 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - California Labor Federation conference mailer, 2009 May (Box 10, Folder 50)
    - Canada union article, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Card Check, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Card check article, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Card check Dana Corporation, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Card Check vs National Labor Relations Board, 1990s (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Century Blvd. civil disobedience, 2006 October 19 (Box 10, Folder 43)
    - Century Blvd. hotels wages, 2005-2006 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Century Blvd. spokesperson information, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Century Plaza, 2004-2011 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Change in hotel ownership articles, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Chants, undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Civil Right Pilgrimage, 2007 March 12 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Community Benefits Agreement Institute, 2005 October 21 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Count of Local 11 Members by Location, 2002 Feb 28 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Dead Tired action special event permit materials, 2007 October (Box 9, Folder 59)
    - Delfina, 2005-2007 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Delfina (Four Points Sheraton / HERE misconduct), 2004 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Double Tree San Jose, 2005-2006 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Downtown Marriot, 2006 June 6 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Employee Free Choice Act fact sheet, undated (Box 9, Folder 71)
    - Employee Manual American Property Management Corporation (text in Spanish), undated (Box 9, Folder 60)
    - Employer's Council hotel ownership, undated (Box 9, Folder 70)
    - Four Points anti-union presentation, undated (Box 9, Folder 61)
    - Freedom to Join a Union (The) pamphlet, undated (Box 10, Folder 59)
    - Glendale Hilton anti-union letters, 2005-2006 (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - Glendale Hilton partnership letter, undated (Box 9, Folder 73)
    - Glendale Hilton press, 2008 June 5 (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - Glendale Hilton revenue sharing article, 2006 February 21 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Grievance procedure, undated (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - Healthcare articles, 2005 September 25-2006 January 9 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Hearing LAX Hilton Hotel, 2006 May 12 (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - HERE newspaper and magazine publications, 1987-1991 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Hilton Hotels Corporation Human Resources Procedures Manual and training documents, undated (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Hilton LAX anti-union propaganda, 2006-2008 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Hilton LAX Boycott, 2006-2007 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Hilton LAX Occupational Safety and Health Appeals complaint, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 79)
    - Hilton Long Beach employee complaints case, 2012 (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - Hilton national agreements, 2002 September 18-2006 July 29 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    - Hilton Team Member Relations Update, International Housekeepers Week catalog, and UCLA Labor Center flyer, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - Hollywood and Vine Mixed-Use Development Project Community Benefits Agreement draft, undated (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - HOST flyers, undated (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - Hotel workers articles, 2005 September 18 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Housekeeping articles, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Housekeeping fact sheet and article, 2006 April 28 (Box 9, Folder 83)
    - Hyatt Employee Handbook, 2012 (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - Hyatt Long Beach policies and training manuals, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Hyatt Long Beach propaganda, 2008 July (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Hyatt Long Beach wage and hours, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Hyatt press article re: Local 11, 2012 April 9 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Immigration social security number no-match, 2012 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Inequality article, 2008 January 19 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - International and out of Los Angeles farmworker campaign clippings, 1993-1994 (Box 10, Folder 44)
    - KWATRA presentation, undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Los Angeles history, undated (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Los Angeles labor article, 2006 September (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Los Angeles Times Antonio Villaraigosa article, 2006 January 26 (Box 10, Folder 45)
    - Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy article, 2013 July-2013 August (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy reports and pamphlet, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Labor history, 2009 February (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Labor Movement article, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Labor union editorial and Bureau of Labor Statistics report, 2008 February 7 (Box 10, Folder 52)
    - LAX Convention Center market analysis report, 2002 December (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - LAX Hilton anti-union, 2006, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - LAX Hilton articles, 2006 May-2008 December (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - LAX Hilton charges against employer, 2008 October (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - LAX Hilton vs National Labor Relations Board, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 46)
    - LAX shuttle drivers, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 55)
    - Living Wage Election Report, 2003 June (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Local 1 (Chicago Tribune Magazine article), 2003 February 16 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Local 11 card check victories flyer, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Local 501 letter, 2006 July 20 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Long Beach articles and reports, undated (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Los Angeles Hotel Employer's Council contract negotiation article, 2004 June 25 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Merger, 1991, 2004, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Middle Class, 2001-2004 (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - Moving Hotels to the High Road report and housekeeping workload checklist, 2003 December (Box 10, Folder 57)
    - National (Hilton LAX letter to employees), 2006 August 30 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - New Union Hotel Standard in Los Angeles highlights of collective bargaining agreement, 1998 April-2004 April (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - National labor Relations Boards Notice of Hearing regarding Glendale Hilton Hotel, 2006 April 27 (Box 10, Folder 35)
    - New York Times anti-union article, 2004 December 14 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Old LAX Files, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 36)
    - Orange City information, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 37)
    - Orange County Communities Organized for Responsible Development report, 2009 February (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - Orange County hotel data, undated (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - Organizing survey (blank), undated (Box 10, Folder 51)
    - Organizing: People, Power and Change course materials, 2008 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Penny Pritzker article, 2008 March 15-16 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Planning Local 11, undated (Box 10, Folder 47)
    - Policy/Legal, 2002-2003 (Box 10, Folder 42)
      Scope and Contents note
      With photocopy of pages from Using the California Labor Laws Offensively: Organizing through Enforcement of State Employment Laws (2002 Edition) publication; and Industrial Welfare Commission Order 5-2001.
    - Poverty article, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Press clippings, 1990s (Box 10, Folder 49)
    - Radisson LAX hotel agreement and worker profile forms, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Right to organize article, 2007 March 6 (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Ritz-Carlton Union Threat seminar, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - San Francisco articles, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - San Francisco meeting, 2006 July 12 (Box 10, Folder 53)
    - Santa Monica Living Wage policy and articles, 2002-2003 (Box 10, Folder 48)
    - Service charge article, 2005 August 26 (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - Sheldon Adelson article, 2008 June 30 (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - Sheraton Gateway card check, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Sheraton Gateway contract, 2007 July 1-2013 June 30 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Sheraton Plaza La Reina, 1980s (Box 10, Folder 54)
    - Southern California Lodging Forecast, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 40)
    - Strike instructions, undated (Box 10, Folder 56)
    - Thoughts on Neutrality Agreements by Richard McCrack, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - Union busters fact sheet, 2004 December 14 (Box 10, Folder 58)
    - Union busting article, 2007 October 9 (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - Union density, undated (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - UNITE HERE merger, undated (Box 10, Folder 60)
    - UNITE HERE Constitution, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Uriostequi and Margarita worker testimonies, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 61)
    - Vegas articles, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 46)
    - Viceroy contract, undated (Box 10, Folder 62)
    - Wage that Meant Middle Class (The) by Louis Uchitelle, 2008 April 20 (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - Wages and hours Starwood Hotel, 2004 September 16 (Box 10, Folder 63)
    - Westin LAX, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 64)
    - Workers United PHX, 2011 May (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - Subseries 1.3: Tom Walsh files, circa 1970s-circa 2004
    Tom Walsh files are subject files documenting Local 11 efforts on behalf of employees employed at Southern California hotels and restaurants. Includes clippings, ephemera, and a small amount of reports and training manuals.
    - AFL-CIO organizing reports, (1989 Fall, 1990 Feb, May-Jun and undated) (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - AFl-CIO publications, (1996 Jan, 2002 Apr-May) (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - AFL-CIO training materials, (1993) (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - Agreement by and between Epicurean, Inc. at Hollywood Park Race Track and HERE Local 11 (Effective April 26, 1992 to April 25, 1995), (undated) (Box 16, Folder 44)
    - Anti-union literature - Aramark, (1997-1998) (Box 15, Folder 38)
    - Banquet server training materials, (undated) (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Belmont, (1999) (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - Biltmore Hotel, (1992) (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Box Tree Restaurant, (1995) (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - California gaming and casinos, (1996-1998) (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - Canter's newspaper clippings, (1991-1992) (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Convention Center, (1993) (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Demanding Your Rights training class, (undated) (Box 16, Folder 41)
    - Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles, (2000) (Box 16, Folder 36)
    - HERE community organizing training, (2000 May) (Box 16, Folder 40)
    - Hollywood Park and Inglewood political community, (1993-1994) (Box 16, Folder 43)
    - Hotel Labor Pact: Room for Everyone article, (1992 Nov 1) (Box 15, Folder 39)
    - Hotel profiles, (early 1990s) (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - Hotel Workers United publication, (undated) (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Hyatt Wilshire, (1989) (Box 16, Folder 27)